<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<s:scufl xmlns:s="http://org.embl.ebi.escience/xscufl/0.1alpha" version="0.2" log="0">
  <s:workflowdescription lsid="urn:lsid:net.sf.taverna:wfDefinition:456e91be-d830-4071-a06c-8cda7d732a26" author="" title="TestWhatizit" />
  <s:processor name="search">
    <s:arbitrarywsdl>
      <s:wsdl>http://www.ebi.ac.uk/webservices/whatizit/ws?wsdl</s:wsdl>
      <s:operation>search</s:operation>
    </s:arbitrarywsdl>
  </s:processor>
  <s:processor name="OMIMdocument" boring="true">
    <s:stringconstant>GENE FUNCTION  Several lines of evidence suggested a critical role for the EZH2 protein during normal and perturbed development of the hematopoietic and central nervous systems. Indeed, the EZH2 protein has been shown to associate with the VAV1 protooncoprotein (164875) and with the XNP protein (300032), the product of a gene associated with mental retardation (Cardoso et al., 1998). 30 PubMed Neighbors  The nature of the EZH2 protein and its mapping to the critical region for malignant myeloid disorders led Cardoso et al. (2000) to propose that the EZH2 gene is involved in the pathogenesis of 7q35-q36 aberrations in myeloid leukemia (Dohner et al., 1998).  Varambally et al. (2002) demonstrated through gene expression profiling that EZH2 is overexpressed in hormone-refractory, metastatic prostate cancer. Small interfering RNA (siRNA) duplexes targeted against EZH2 reduced the amounts of EZH2 protein present in prostate cells and also inhibited cell proliferation in vitro. Ectopic expression of EZH2 in prostate cells induced transcriptional repression of a specific cohort of genes. Gene silencing mediated by EZH2 requires the SET domain and is attenuated by inhibiting histone deacetylase activity. Amounts of both EZH2 mRNA and EZH2 protein were increased in metastatic prostate cancer. In addition, clinically localized prostate cancers that expressed higher concentrations of EZH2 showed a poorer prognosis. Thus, Varambally et al. (2002) concluded that dysregulated expression of EZH2 may be involved in the progression of prostate cancer as well as being a marker that distinguishes indolent prostate cancer from those at risk of lethal progression. 30 PubMed Neighbors  Cao et al. (2002) reported the purification and characterization of an EED-EZH2 complex, the human counterpart of the Drosophila ESC-E(Z) complex. Cao et al. (2002) demonstrated that the complex specifically methylates nucleosomal histone H3 (see 601128) at lysine-27 (H3-K27). Using chromatin immunoprecipitation assays, Cao et al. (2002) showed that H3-K27 methylation colocalizes with, and is dependent on, E(Z) binding at an 'Ultrabithorax' (Ubx) Polycomb response element, and that this methylation correlates with Ubx expression. Methylation on H3-K27 facilitates binding of Polycomb, a component of the Polycomb repressive complex 1 (PRC1 complex), to the histone H3 N-terminal tail. Thus, Cao et al. (2002) concluded that their studies established a link between histone methylation and Polycomb group-mediated gene silencing. The complex responsible for histone methyltransferase activity included EZH2, SUZ12 (606245) and EED (605984). EZH2 contains a SET domain, a signature motif for all known histone lysine methyltransferases except the H3-K79 methyltransferase DOT1, and is therefore likely to be the catalytic subunit. 30 PubMed Neighbors  Plath et al. (2003) demonstrated that transient recruitment of the EED-EZH2 complex to the inactive X chromosome occurs during initiation of X inactivation in both extraembryonic and embryonic cells and is accompanied by H3-K27 methylation. Recruitment of the complex and methylation on the inactive X depend on Xist (314670) RNA but are independent of its silencing function. Plath et al. (2003) concluded that taken together, their results suggest a role for EED-EZH2-mediated H3-K27 methylation during initiation of both imprinted and random X inactivation and demonstrate that H3-K27 methylation is not sufficient for silencing of the inactive X. 30 PubMed Neighbors  Cha et al. (2005) showed that AKT (164730) phosphorylates EZH2 at serine-21 and suppresses its methyltransferase activity by impeding EZH2 binding to histone H3, which results in a decrease of lysine-27 trimethylation and derepression of silenced genes. Cha et al. (2005) concluded that their results imply that AKT regulates the methylation activity, through phosphorylation of EZH2, which may contribute to oncogenesis. 30 PubMed Neighbors  Vire et al. (2006) showed that the silencing pathways of the polycomb group (PcG) and DNA methyltransferases systems are mechanically linked. They found that the PcG protein EZH2 interacts--within the context of the Polycomb repressive complexes 2 and 3 (PRC2/3)--with DNA methyltransferases DNMT1 (126375), DNMT3A (602769), and DNMT3B (602900) and associates with DNMT activity in vivo. Chromatin immunoprecipitations indicated that binding of DNMTs to several EZH2-repressed genes depends on the presence of EZH2. Furthermore, Vire et al. (2006) showed by bisulfite genomic sequencing that EZH2 is required for DNA methylation of EZH2-target promoters. Vire et al. (2006) concluded that their results suggest that EZH2 serves as a recruitment platform for DNA methyltransferases, thus highlighting a previously unrecognized direct connection between 2 key epigenetic repression systems. 30 PubMed Neighbors  As indicated by the work of Kamminga et al. (2006), EZH2 is, like latexin (LXN; 609305), a stem cell regulator.  Ulcerative colitis is a chronic inflammatory condition characterized by three phases: active, regression and remission phase. The active phase is followed by atrophy of the large intestinal mucosa. Although its evaluation is sometimes difficult, quantification of ceratin mucosal parameters can be used as an accessory method. The aim of the study was to determine the parameters of linear micrometry in order to estimate the regeneration of the large intestinal mucosa in ulcerative colitis, and to evaluate the efficiacy of this method in everyday work. The measurements were performed on routine bioptic samples after qualitative histologic analysis and determination of the type and stage of the disease. The measurements were carried out to determine: the number of crypts per unit length, the height of crypt epithelium, diameter of crypts, their lumen and interstices; also, the quotient between the diameters of crypts and interstices was calculated. The analysis of the measured parameters points to presence and degree of regeneration and/or atrophy of mucosa, particularly by following the parameters of crypt epithelium. Linear measurements can be used in estimation of regeneration and atrophy of large intestinal mucosa.</s:stringconstant>
  </s:processor>
  <s:processor name="whatizitPipeline" boring="true">
    <s:stringconstant>whatizitDisease</s:stringconstant>
  </s:processor>
</s:scufl>

